שבוע טוב, Shavua Tov, גוט מועד, Gut Moed, fifth day of the
Omer. Today's דף Daf is מ"ח, Mem Ches, 48, almost the number
of days in the Omer. Anyway, we pick up on the middle
of מ"ז עמוד ב' Mem Zayin Amud Bais and we're in the
middle of an interesting question: can somebody marry a woman, a man
marry a woman with a מלווה? Milveh? Not by waiving the loan,
but by essentially giving her back the money she owes him. But
that money is only now an abstract debt. And then that led
to a question of מלווה להוצאה ניתנה. Milveh le'hotza'ah nitnah. Maybe you
can't even do it even if the cash is still in her
hands, the original money that he still lent her, but that's no
longer considered his money. As soon as he gives it over, maybe
that's hers and she just owes him money now. And the גמרא
Gemara has been arguing even though there seems some, as there's some
Tannaitic debate about this, but in order to defend the position of
whose position was this by the way? רב? Rav? Yes, רב. Rav.
The גמרא Gemara has been arguing that everybody agrees מלווה להוצאה ניתנה
Milveh le'hotza'ah nitnah and that at the most there's a debate when
that loan becomes actually when she actually takes possession of that
money to be fully obligated and he can't retract and so on
and that's considered her money now, it's just an abstract debt. Whether
it's as soon as the money is handed over or only once
she starts using it. And then the גמרא Gemara says well what
would be the ramification of that beyond the question about marrying a
woman when it's considered to be that she's taken possession. So first
the גמרא Gemara had two נפקא מינות. Nafka minas. One נפקא מינא
Nafka mina would be if some accident happens to the money, a
wind comes and blows it out of her hand, whose money was
it that just got lost? And the other question would be whether
he can change his mind and ask for the money back. So
the גמרא Gemara said actually everybody should hold, even if she doesn't
take possession of the money until she starts spending it, everybody would
hold that she's liable for losses immediately. Just like when you lend
an object, the person doesn't take possession—I lend you my car, you
don't own the car, it's still my car—but as soon as you
take not ownership over it but you take it under your control,
you become a שואל Sho'el and you're liable for losses. So here
too, as soon as the money is handed over then she becomes
a שואל Sho'el and she's liable for losses even though it doesn't
even if we were to say that it doesn't become her money
until she begins to spend it. So the one נפקא מינא Nafka
mina besides marrying her with that money would be whether you can
ask for it back and retract. Now, by the way, that's not
logical that you should be able to do that either, right? If
I lend you my car and you sign the contract and you
take the keys, right, it's still my car, but I can't ask
for it back during the period of the contract. So anyway, but
the so you could have said the same here. Maybe it doesn't
become your money yet, but maybe I can't retract once I hand
it over. Anyway, let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. So that's
where we pick up. Yes. You just said something that really clarified.
Are we assuming that all these scenarios, let's say a שואל, Sho'el,
is always a written
contractual... No. So בעל פה, Bal peh, right? Yeah, so I mean
I was using contract in a contemporary sense, but yeah, it doesn't
matter. It becomes a binding agreement. Right. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says like this.
Okay, so אלא הכא מלווה ברשות בעלים לחזרה איכא בינייהו. Ella hacha
milveh birshus ba'alin le'chazara ika beinaihu. It's exactly opposite from the תוספות
דכולי עלמא, Tosafot de'chulei alma, ד' כ"א, Daled chaf aleph, and its
word בינייהו. Beinaihu. So here the גמרא Gemara says, so certainly
you'd be liable for losses as soon as the money was handed
over. But the question when it becomes your money is the question
about whether the owners can retract. And that's the issue. Okay, so
that's what it says.
אלא, Ella, where was it? אלא, Ella, I just lost my place
again, אלא הכא מלווה ברשות בעלים לחזרה איכא בינייהו. Ella hacha milveh
birshus ba'alin le'chazara ika beinaihu. That would be the question: immediately or
only once the money begins to be that they can't retract immediately
or they can't retract only once the money begins to be spent.
And it would be a similar question of marrying a woman with
that money, when it stops being the original owner's money. Okay, ואלא
הא דאמר רב הונא, Ve'ella hadamar Rav Huna, so according to that,
that which רב הונא Rav Huna says: השואל קרדום מחבירו, Hasho'el kardom
me'chavero, if you borrow a hammer from me... ביקע בו קנאו, Bika
bo kena'o, once you start banging with it you own it, meaning
it we'll see what own means because it's still my hammer. I'm
sorry, an axe, excuse me, I don't know why I said קרדום
לחפור בו. Kardom lachpor bo. Right, right, right, it's a good point,
yeah, I'm sorry where I said that. Okay, yeah, okay, an axe,
but wait a minute, you don't dig with an axe. It's weird,
קרדום לחפור בו, Kardom lachpor bo, right? Is this פרקי אבות? Pirkei
Avot? No, no, wait, wait. How do you say a hammer in
modern Hebrew?
פטיש. Patish. Ah, okay, okay. Anyway, so, okay, an axe, what? Yeah,
a spade? I think it's a spade or a hoe. A hatchet.
But here the verb indicates that you're chopping wood. Okay, fine. All
right, so we got... okay, so you borrow an axe, thank you.
ביקע בו קנאו, Bika bo kena'o, once you start chopping with it
you take possession of it. לא ביקע בו, Lo bika bo, if
before the borrower takes starts chopping, לא קנאו. Lo kena'o. It does
not take possession. Now it obviously is obvious yes, it obviously is
owned by the original owner, so what does take possession mean? So
we think take possession means the question about both maybe both of
these things, right, when does he become liable for damages and whether
the original owner can go back on the transaction. Okay, but let's
at least focus on חזרה chazarah going back on the transaction, which
is what we just sort of said was the debate here around
you know around the lending of the money. So the גמרא Gemara
says לימא כתנאי אמרה לשמעתיה. leima ketannai amrah lishmateih.
So are we going to say that this issue about what do
you call it about retracting is really the you know this statement
excuse me of רב הונא Rav Huna is really only one position
of a debate of תנאים? Tannaim? Because by the money we're saying
you might not take there's two opinions when you can go back
on it. Either you can't go back immediately or you only can't
go back once the money is spent, right? And here we're saying
that רב הונא Rav Huna is saying that you only can take
possession once you start using it, which would be the parallel of
the money being spent. Yes? Is it what... this do you pay
for this hatchet when you... No, you're a borrower. Yeah, yeah, you're
not a renter, you're a borrower. Right. Okay. And that's why you're
fully liable for any losses. So רב הונא Rav Huna says you
only take possession, which we're assuming means the owner can't retract, right,
once you start using it, okay, but we actually said that there
were two opinions about that in terms of a loan, whether it
was immediate or once you start using it. So is he only
saying like one of those opinions? לימא כתנאי אמרה לשמעתיה leima ketannai
amrah lishmateih is he only saying like one of those opinions of
the תנאים? Tannaim? The גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, no. עד כאן
לא פליגי אלא במלווה, ad kan lo peligi ela bemilveh, thank you.
The only debate is with a loan, that the whole point of
the loan was to spend the money and give back different money.
So there you could say that as soon as the money is
handed over, it stops being the original owner's because the whole point
was you're not you know you're giving up on this particular money
here and you know it's going to be different money you're getting
back. So as soon as it leaves your possession, that's it, you're
done. Okay. אבל בשאלה דהדרא בעינא aval beshe'elah dehadra be'eina that by
lending an object that you're going to get back the object itself,
so yours, the original owner's possession of that or you know is
still present, I mean and even after the guy really does you
know is an official borrower you still own the object and you're
getting the object back. In that case you could say דברי הכל
ביקע בו אין לא ביקע בו לא. divrei hakol bika bo in
lo bika bo lo. You could say that everybody would agree in
that case that it's only once you start using it because my
sense of ownership is greater. Now by the way תוספות Tosafot points
out, which we would expect because of this logical
comparison whatever not necessarily but anyway תוספות Tosafot points out that in
terms of חייב באונסין, chayav be'onsin, okay
because we said we said two things right, we said here we
said right if you're giving money right so if you're giving money
and it's a loan right so we said חייב באונסין chayav be'onsin
was
was immediate okay
and חזרה chazarah was a debate whether it's you know one position
is immediate
and the other and the other position is only when start spending,
okay.
Now here we're talking about a about a hatchet, okay, שאלה, she'elah,
a hatchet, let me try try to draw a hatchet, I don't
know. Okay
anyway so we said that here it's only when you start using
it, alright. So the גמרא Gemara says that makes sense because even
this position of immediate that's only when you're dealing with cash that
the whole thing is you basically are giving up that those dollars
and getting different dollars back. But something that's by an actual object
everybody would agree it's when you start using it, okay. The only
reason that here they say immediate and that's basically the way we
פסקן pasquen by the way you know which is מלווה להוצאה ניתנה
milve lehotza'a nitnah immediately as it's handed over like that's only because
you basically are giving up on the actual cash. But how about
the issue of חייב באונסין? chayav be'onsin? So remember how did the
גמרא Gemara say why did the גמרא Gemara say חייב באונסין chayav
be'onsin was immediate? Because it said this is no different than lending
objects, right? Remember the גמרא Gemara said that? Here of course it
would be immediate because when you lend objects the obligation comes immediately
even though obviously you're staying in possession of the object but the
person becomes obligated immediately. So here although the גמרא Gemara doesn't say
it תוספות Tosafot points out that the same is true by by
you know by the hatchet because that's what where we're learning it
from. So as soon as it gets under your control as soon
as it gets under your physical control you're liable for any damages.
Whether I can still back out how much do I still have
my hand on it that I can still back out here maybe
I still have my hand on it until you start using it
but here maybe I give up my sort of sense of holding
on to it right away because I'm going to get different money
back, okay. And immediately I mean when I like lift it up?
Yes yes as soon as I hand it over right, okay. All
right anyway at this point so now let's so now let's so
the גמרא Gemara now continues let's take a look.
Okay. נימא כתנאי. Nima Ketannai. Now let's say this issue of מקדש
במלוה, mekadesh bimilveh, so now we're done with this comparison and this
is back to the, to the hatchet and to שאילה, she'eilah, these
two issues about retracting and liable for damages, okay, and we're back
to the basic idea that מלוה להוצאה ניתנה, milveh le-hotza'ah nittena, I
give you the money, it's your money now, it's not my money
anymore, I can't marry a woman with it after I've given it
over as a loan, and that's Rav's position that you cannot be
מקדש במלוה. mekadesh bimilveh. Now the גמרא Gemara wants to say, you
know what, maybe that's a debate of תנאים Tannaim whether you can
marry a woman with a loan.
נימא כתנאי, Nima Ketannai, let's say this is a debate of
תנאים. Tannaim. המקדש בשטר חוב, Ha-mekadesh bish'tar hov, a man says to
a woman, marry me with this document of debt, with this IOU,
או שהיה לו מלוה ביד אחרים והרשה עליהן, o she-hayah lo milveh
beyad aherim ve-hirsah aleihen, or other people owe me
money and I basically authorized you to collect it. So I transfer
the debt that other people owe me to you, you the woman.
So what's the הלכה? halakhah? רבי מאיר אומר מקודשת וחכמים אומרים אינו
מקודשת, Rabbi Meir omer mekudeshet va-hakhamim omer eino mekudeshet, she's married, and
the sages say she's not married. Now, certainly the second case, I
transfer a debt to you, that's an object of value, it might
be an abstract object, but it's certainly an object of value, right,
so what should that debate be about? But before we even get
there, you said I'm מקדש mekadesh you with the הנאה hana'ah that
you're getting or the presumed benefit you're getting from collecting the debt,
like if you just gave her a piece of paper, just transferring
the שטר חוב, shtar hov, yeah, but all right, well, we can
talk about it, but it sounds like in the case where I
say I am authorizing you to collect the debt, that what I'm
benefiting, what I'm marrying you with is that thing that I've just
given you, the authority to collect the debt, right, and that would
seem that that's an object of value, I'm not marrying you with
the money of the debt, I'm now giving you the authority to
collect the debt and he's מקדש mekadesh me with this. So anyway,
we'll see about it in the גמרא, Gemara, okay, but yes, you
could here as well distinguish between you being מקדש mekadesh with the
thing of value that was given or with the money that has
yet to be collected. Okay, but anyway, that's the second case when
you're giving over a loan,
money owed to you. But the גמרא Gemara wants to focus on
what's the first case where it says you give her the IOU.
Whose IOU are you giving her? An IOU that somebody else has
to you? Well, that's already the second case. It sounds like it,
so the גמרא's Gemara going to say, might be the IOU of
money she owes you, and then we're into the case of מקדש
במלוה. mekadesh bimilveh. So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara
says, האי שטר חוב היכי דמי, Hai shtar hov heikhi dami, when
you give her over, there's got to be a better word for
שטר חוב shtar hov than IOU, okay, anyway, that creditor document or
that loan document, what's the case? אילימא שטר חוב דאחרים, Ilei-ma shtar
hov de-aherim, if it's other people owe you money and you have
it in a document, היינו מלוה ביד אחרים, hainu milveh beyad aherim,
that's the second case of giving her over a debt that's owed
to you. אלא לאו שטר חוב דידה, Ela la'av shtar hov dide-hah,
it must be that it's the document that she owes you
money, okay, and ובמקדש במלוה
קא מיפלגי, u-vi-mekadesh bimilveh ka mipalgi, it sounds like at least the
first case, we'll figure out what the second debate is about because
that's marrying her with other people's money, but the first case sounds
like if the case is she owes you money and we see
that there's a debate whether that works. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says no, לעולם שטר חוב דאחרים, le'olam shtar hov de-aherim, which by
the way makes sense, right, it would be bizarre that they would
be arguing about two different cases because there's different logic why the
issue about marrying her with her own debt and marrying her with
somebody else's debt. And there's a debate, so it seems like I
would more be inclined to say this reading, that they're really debating
fundamentally the same type of category, other people owing you money and
transferring that. So that's what the גמרא Gemara says. No, the first
case actually is
a document of debt that other people owe you. Okay, so לעולם
le'olam says
the גמרא, Gemara, שטר חוב דאחרים. shtar hov de-aherim. והכא במלוה בשטר
במלוה על פה קא מיפלגי. ve-hakha bi-milveh bi-shtar bi-milveh al peh ka
mipalgi. The difference is is there a document or not a document.
In one case, you hand her over the document that somebody else,
ראובן Reuven owes you money, here's the document, you go ahead and
collect it, which now really you would think she should be מקודשת.
mekudeshet. You've given her a physical object that has a market value.
Why should she not be מקודשת? mekudeshet? The second case, it's all
abstract. Okay, but at least we're fundamentally dealing you're handing her over
a debt that's owed to you. So now let's understand what that
debate is about.
במלוה בשטר במאי פליגי, Bi-milveh bi-shtar be-mai palgi, so what's the debate
when there is a document? Why should that not be good? בפלוגתא
דרבי ורבנן קא מיפלגי, Be-falguta de-Rabbi ve-Rabbanan ka mipalgi, the debate of
רבי Rabbi and the רבנן. Rabbanan. דתניא, De-tanya, as we taught in
a ברייתא, braita, אותיות נקנות במסירה. Otiyyot niknot bi-mesirah. So how do
you transfer a document of debt? Okay, so that's called אותיות, otiyyot,
like, you know, like letters, like you're not, you know, you're not
actually giving her the money, you're giving her the right to collect
the money and it's sort of articulated in this document, so it's
funny that that's referred to as אותיות. otiyyot. How do you קונה
koneh the letters? How do you קונה koneh not the piece of
paper but the rights that are implicit in this document? Okay, so
one answer is במסירה, bi-mesirah, by handing over the physical document. document
that transfers it. Okay, one there's questions about supporting documentation to prove
that this person now has legally purchased this and hasn't just found
a שטר חוב, shtar chov, but anyway, okay, by handing it over,
דברי רבי, divrei Rabbi, that's what Rabbi said. וחכמים אומרים, ve-Chachamim omrim,
בין שכתב ולא מסר, bein she-kasav ve-lo masar, whether you wrote out
supporting documentation, I'm transferring my loan to Reuben but you haven't given
him the document, או בין שמסר ולא כתב, o bein she-masar ve-lo
kasav, or you gave him the document without the supporting documentation, okay,
לא קנה, lo kanah, Reuben does not take possession of the debt,
עד שיכתוב וימסור, ad she-yichtov ve-yimsor, until you both write out the
identifying him as the new creditor and handing over the document. Okay,
so there's a question how do you take possession? So the case
would be that you handed over the document but you didn't write
the supporting documentation. And that's why there's a question whether the woman
is married or not. מר אית ליה דרבי, mar is lei de-Rabbi,
one holds like Rabbi, which is that you need that you need
that only handing over the document suffices, so that would say מקודשת,
mekudeshes, because that's all you did, you handed her the שטר. shtar.
ומר לית ליה דרבי, u-mar leis lei de-Rabbi, and the other one
doesn't hold of Rabbi and says no, you didn't she didn't take
full possession of the debt yet. Now that's funny, because then they're
really not debating a question about קידושין. kiddushin. They're debating like you
could have said, if you give a woman a ring and you
only pick it up one טפח tefach and not three טפחים, tefachim,
right, is she מקודשת mekudeshes or not? Like then it's not a
debate about קידושין. kiddushin. It's a question about how you take possession
of it. Anyway, that's one thing the גמרא Gemara is saying, is
they're not really debating קידושין, kiddushin, they're debating whether she's taking possession
of not the physical document, but of the debt that's in the
document. Yes. Is it impossible to explain the case of שטר חוב
shtar chov that meaning he owes her money and he's saying that
this שטר חוב shtar chov that I owe you, I want you
to be מקודשת mekudeshes to me? I mean I repay you back
like $200, I want this to be paid back in lieu of
that? No, that's not... A, it's not being מקדש mekadesh with a
שטר חוב, shtar chov, and B, then it's giving her money that's...
how could you be מקדש mekadesh with money that's already hers? Anyway,
it's not. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'is
eima, if you want you could say, דכולי עלמא לית להו דרבי,
de-chulei alma leis lehu de-Rabbi, everybody rejects Rabbi, you need both to
hand it over and to write. והכא בדרב פפא קמיפלגי, ve-hacha bi-de-Rav
Pappa k-miflegi, they debate Rav Pappa. Okay,
because what you did is you did write her, you did hand
it to her and you did write supporting documentation, but the question
is, did you write the documentation in the right way? Okay, דאמר
רב פפא, de-amar Rav Pappa, because Rav Pappa says, האי מאן דזבין
שטר לחבריה, hai man de-zavin shtar le-chavrei, if you sell a debt
in a written document to your friend, in a document of loan,
צריך למכתב ליה, tzarich le-michtav lei, when you write the supporting documentation,
you hand over the loan document, but what do you how do
you identify him as the new creditor? What you write is קני
לך איהו וכל שיעבודיה, knei lach ihu ve-chol shibudei, take possession of
it and all of the liens that come with it. So you
have to write that, and if you don't write with all of
the liens that come with it, he doesn't really take possession of
the debt. So מר אית ליה דרב פפא, mar is lei de-Rav
Pappa, one holds of Rav Pappa and therefore and מר לית ליה
דרב פפא, u-mar leis lei de-Rav Pappa, one doesn't hold and says
you don't need to write that. So again, it's a very non-קידושין
kiddushin debate. Okay, it's a case where you gave her the document
with a supporting documentation, the שטר shtar with supporting documentation, but you
didn't have a line in the document. So one says oh, you
haven't taken possession, you didn't have the right line. And the other
says you don't need that line. Okay, so anyway, a very side
debate. ואיבעית אימא, ve-iba'is eima, if you want you could say,
דכולי עלמא אית להו דרב פפא, de-chulei alma is lehu de-Rav Pappa,
everybody agrees with Rav Pappa, you needed to have that line in
it. And you have that line in it. So you handed her
the שטר חוב, shtar chov, you gave her the supporting documentation, it
had the right line in it, take possession of the debt and
of the liens. והכא בשמואל קמיפלגי... ve-hacha bi-Shmuel k-miflegi... so what's the
debate? You gave her a physical object of value. What's the debate?
The debate is שמואל. Shmuel. דאמר שמואל, de-amar Shmuel, because Shmuel says,
המוכר שטר חוב לחבירו, ha-mocher shtar chov le-chaviro, so we're using this
as an opportunity to deal with every single debate that exists relating
to selling a שטר חוב. shtar chov. Okay, so you sell a
שטר חוב shtar chov to your friend, וחזר ומחלו מחול. ve-chazar u-machalo
machul. Now, if I go ahead, I sell Michael the, you know,
Dov Levie here owes me $1,000, I sell to Michael a discount,
only $800 because I'm not sure if I'm ever going to get
him to pay up. Okay, so $800 and I give you over
the document and I write קני לך איהו וכל שיעבודיה. knei lach
ihu ve-chol shibudei. Okay, now I go afterwards and I say, Dov,
want to get out of the $1,000 you owe Michael? Give me
50 bucks. You give me 50 bucks, I say המוחל ha-mochel the
debt to you. Okay, and now Michael can't collect. What what's the
logic of that? The logic of that is that there's a difference
here between okay, how do you transfer a debt? Because the debt
is if it's seen as a personal obligation. You got the money
from me, you owe me the money. How does that become an
abstract thing? It's not a physical object, it's a personal debt that
you owe me. By the way, if if if the borrower dies
and he doesn't leave over any land, I can't collect from the
heirs. What what's the logic of that? The logic of that is
because it's a flow... flesh-mate account. Yes, because the logic is is
because it's a personal obligation, it's first and foremost a personal obligation,
right, and if there is a way that it doesn't relate to
the person himself, it's because
What do I transfer to Michael? Am I able to make Michael
me? Now he directly owes Michael the money, or no? What I
say is, he still owes me the money. You know what I'm
transferring to you? One of two things. Either what I'm saying is,
that I'm having like a what's it called, not an automatic deposit,
but an automatic transfer. So by giving it over to you, what
I'm saying is, or I'm sort of making you my power of
attorney slash automatic transfer. So once you have the right to bring
him to court, and once he pays up, it's sort of you're
collecting my debt, it goes to you, but through me. Okay, or
the other way of understanding it is that what I'm basically transferring
to you is the liens, but not really the debt. Okay, that's
the קני לך איהו וכל שעבודיה. k'meilecha ve'chol shibuda. Either way, if
he still fundamentally owes me the money, I could be מוחל mochel
the money to him. I could be מוחל, mochel, and now there's
nothing left for you to collect. Now the question is, you're going
to want to take me to court and sue me for damages.
So that's a debate in the גמרא Gemara about דן דיני דגרמי,
dan dinei de'garmi, because I only indirectly caused you a loss, I
didn't directly break an object of yours. But maybe you might be
able to sue me for damages. But that's separate from the question
of whether I have still the power to annul the loan. And
שמואל Shmuel says I have the power to annul the loan. You
can't abstract it like that. Right, you can't really fully transfer. If
Ben Bernanke had known this גמרא, Gemara, the housing market would not
have crashed in 2008.
The whole thing was, yeah, but of course the whole economy would
be different if you couldn't really transfer loans. By the way, תוספות
Tosafot has a different explanation, a less conceptual one. If you take
a look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות Tosafot says, היש מפרש המוכר שטר
חוב לחברו, hayesh meforash hamocher shtar chov lachaveiro, תוספות Tosafot
says יש מפרשים היינו טעמא דמוחל מוחל, yeish mefarshim haynu taama d'mochel
mochel, here's why it works, משום דקנין שטרות לאו מדאורייתא, mishum d'kinyan
shtarot lav mi'deorayta, I mean it's sort of similar, but it's saying
like it's not conceptual. It's saying like there's no דאורייתא deorayta way
of transferring a debt. It's only rabbinic. Like מטלטלין? metaltelin?
No, no, no, because it's an abstract thing. You can't really, so
it's only rabbinically that Michael owes the debt. Okay, ולא אלים לאפקועי
כח הראשון velo alim l'afkeie koach harishon
and therefore the דאורייתא deorayta level is still always present. Okay, so
it's a similar idea but the thing I said was I think
a nicer conceptual way of understanding. Fundamentally, דב Dov still owes me
the money and you just now have the right to somehow collect
and pocket it. Okay, so שמואל Shmuel says המוכר שטר חוב לחברו
וחזר ומחלו מחול. hamocher shtar chov lachaveiro v'chazar u'machalo machul. ואפילו יורש
מוחל. va'afilu yoresh mochel. Even an heir can, meaning, even if the
guy, the original creditor has died and he left behind an heir,
right, this is the interesting thing, because the personal obligation does go
to the heir, right? So the heir now has the right to
annul the debt. It's a little ironic, right?
The debtor dies without liens and the heirs don't have an obligation
to pay off. But the creditor dies and the money still owed
to the creditor's heirs. Just that's an interesting asymmetry, by the way.
Anyway, but even the heir can go ahead and annul the debt.
Now, how is that relevant? So I go ahead and I marry
this woman with this money that other people owe me and I
give her the שטר חוב shtar chov and I totally transfer the
debt. Does it work? And here's why it might be a קידושין
kiddushin issue. She does owe the debt, own the debt, but and
the debt has a market value, even acknowledging שמואל Shmuel that I
have the power to annul it, that affects the market value, but
there still is a market value. Okay, but the question is, even
though it's a market value, you might have this issue called לא
סמכא דעתה, lo samcha da'ata, right, which we've had before, right, which
is that she's not feeling confident about the object you gave her.
And therefore, that might prevent it from working as כסף קידושין. kesef
kiddushin. Okay, so let's take a look. דמר אית ליה דשמואל, demar
it lei d'Shmuel, one holds like שמואל Shmuel and therefore says that
it's not really a good object to marry with, she doesn't feel
confident that she'll be able to collect. ומר לית ליה דשמואל, vmar
leit lei d'Shmuel, because I can still be מוחל, mochel, right, which
is funny. It still has a market value, but nevertheless, if she's
not feeling confident, that somehow prevents it from working. דמר אית ליה
דשמואל ומר לית ליה דשמואל. demar it lei d'Shmuel vmar leit lei
d'Shmuel. And one doesn't hold like it and therefore she would always
be able to collect and it's good for כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin.
Now, how would this at all be relevant? I would have thought
that discomfort would come also from something else. So you מקדש mekadesh
this woman with an IOU, with a bond, with a debt.
But there's always a ספק safek whether you can really get the
money. Yeah, but that's different. That's טורח turach and almost an אונס.
oness. Yeah, I understand, but that's different, because you know again, I
think it's a similar question because you know, any of those concerns
translate into the market value, but it's still worth a פרוטה. prutah.
But I think there's still a difference when you're fully in control
and you understand that that's a risk that you're taking, right, and
that and that you still got something of real value as opposed
to something that as a random event it could become worthless and
I can't control that. Right? So yes, it's a certain risk, I
understand that there's that risk that affects the market value, but there's
a complete random event out of my control that I can't accept.
And you understand that that's a risk that you're taking, right, and
that and that you still got something of real value as opposed
to something that's a random event, it could become worthless and I
can't control that. Right? So yes, it's a certain risk, I understand
that there's that risk that affects the market value, but there's a
complete random event out of my control that I can't expect and
whatever. So have I really feel? But it's interesting because bottom line
is, and this is why the question about is קידושי כסף kiddushei
kesef of אשה isha the same as other קידושי כסף? kiddushei kesef?
It's like, who really cares that you have this anxiety. You got
something of market value and you could turn around and sell it
to somebody else for about the same amount. So who really cares
if you feel confident or not? So I think it's interesting, just
סמכא דעתא samcha da'ata idea. Even if she says she's okay, we
follow what she says? No, yeah, that's also a good question about
what you look at as taste, I guess. Anyway, let's take a
look at the next case. So the גמרא Gemara says איבעית אימא
ibayit eima if you want I could say דכולי עלמא אית להו
דשמואל. d'chulei alma it lehu d'Shmuel. Everybody holds of Shmuel. והכא באשה
קמיפלגי. v'hacha b'isha kamiflegi.
And the question is by a woman, meaning רש"י Rashi says that
actually what I just said is true is not specific to קידושין.
kiddushin. That if I were to give it to a- use it
to buy a field, everybody would agree it would be no good
to buy a field because the person who I transferred that to
says this guy might might annul the debt and I'll be left
empty-handed. So it does not count enough as כסף kesef because of
that anxiety around whether- right, but for buying a field everybody agrees
it would not work. The only question is maybe it works by
קידושין. kiddushin. Why should קידושין kiddushin be different? Because והכא באשה קמיפלגי.
v'hacha b'isha kamiflegi. מר סבר אשה סמכא דעתא. mar savar isha samcha
da'ata. No,
no, the case of a woman and not just a woman, the
woman who's becoming your wife with this money, she does not have
this anxiety. Why does she not have this anxiety? Because מימר אמרה
לא שביק לדידי ומחיל לאחריני. meimar amra lo shavik l'didi u'machil l'achrinei.
You know what it means for him to be מוחל mochal the
debt? He's preferring, you know, doing something nice for that other guy
and robbing me of this object of value. So at least when
they're first getting married she's not afraid of that. What happens to
the relationship afterwards I can't tell you, okay? But at that moment
she feels confident that he is not going to double-cross me and,
you know, do a favor to that guy and make me lose
out. So it's- so it's- constant- the- comes to romance, I guess.
Exactly. Exactly. Okay. ומר סבר אשה נמי לא סמכא דעתא. u'mar savar
isha nami lo samcha da'ata.
No, even when they're getting married she's not sure what he's going
to do with it. Okay. But actually again what's interesting is that
רש"י Rashi says that according to this everybody would agree to buy
a field from a stranger, right, he says I don't know tomorrow
he'll turn around and be מוחל mochal and it would not work
as כסף. kesef. So it's quite interesting that something could have a
clear market value and nevertheless not operate as כסף kesef because of
this anxiety around it. Okay. It might have to do combined with
the fact that it's abstract. Right? If I actually gave you a
physical object of market value with some type of similar anxiety I
wouldn't- don't know what the case would be. Presumably that definitely would
work. Okay. But this is just an abstract thing that we're considering
as כסף. kesef. So to consider this abstract thing as כסף kesef
with this anxiety around it might not work. When we talk about
holding like Shmuel and not holding like Shmuel do we mean that-
סמיכות דעת semichut da'at by everyone else or just simply the very...
No, debating whether it's true, whether the original creditor can be מוחל.
mochal. Okay. So that's- so what's the debate by can you marry
a woman with a- written IOU that other people owe you, a
debt, a- you know, a document of debt? So mostly it's a
debate around what you hold about documents of debt and how exactly
you take possession in certain details. It's certainly not a debate about
קידושין. kiddushin. Okay. That's question number one. Okay. Yes. How would the
תורה, Torah, the תלמוד Talmud create a system with this concept of
being
מוחל? mochal?
Right. It's completely impractical. Now you know if you back that up
with a דינא דגרמי dina d'garmi with a type of damages that
you can sue for, hopefully it'll limit the cases about this but
it's still highly inefficient and impractical. Why allow it to work and
then allow somebody to sue for damages, right, as opposed to just
not allowing it to work? Right? And obviously and I mean, you
know, I'm not an economist but I do understand that- that, you
know, that economy's really able to grow when you're able to sort
of transfer, you know, credit and so on, right? So- so this
makes it a very inelastic economy, right? That like who's really going
to be buying up debt and so on? It's perfectly like you
alluded to. Right. Right. And it- yeah, no and it reflects, you
know, obviously an economy that's much more originally agrarian, you know, and
not commercial and, you know, and as more personal rather than whatever-
anyway but yeah. Alright so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. במלווה על פה במאי פליגי? b'milveh al peh b'mai palgi? What
do they debate when it's an oral loan, whether you can transfer
that? Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says because that may be all
the problems with a written document should be by an oral loan
plus possibly other ones. So the גמרא Gemara says בדרב הונא אמר
רב. b'd'Rav Huna amar Rav. They debate Rav Huna who said in
the name of Rav. דאמר רב הונא אמר רב d'amar Rav Huna
amar Rav מנה לי בידך תנהו לפלוני במעמד שלשתן. maneh li b'yadcha
tenahu l'ploni b'ma'amad shloshtan. So you're- Michael owes me money and I
say Michael, you know that hundred dollars you owe me, give it
to David. Okay. And we're all three standing here. So קנה. kana.
So now David owns the money. I can transfer something if we're
all three present. It's a special קניין kinyan that the חז"ל Chazal
gave us. And by the way, that's a whole other debate. Is
that a special קניין kinyan or is that just like a logical
consequence of us all standing here and agreeing? But let's just consider
it for now a special קניין kinyan for transferring oral loans. Okay,
so if we're all three here, then you could transfer an oral
loan to a woman and marry her with it. So what do
you debate? Well, we debate whether we hold like Rav Huna who
says במעמד שלשתן b'ma'amad shloshtan works. One guy says it works and
the other guy says it doesn't work. Okay, that's what the גמרא
Gemara says. Okay, let's take a look at the next step. By
the way, תוספות Tosafot says that in this case, you wouldn't have
to do any of the things we discussed before. You wouldn't—first of
all, in that case, תוספות Tosafot says, and this solves a little
bit of the problem, that I can't be מוחל mochel it. Why
not? If I—because that's just the way they were מתקין מעמד שלשתן.
matkin ma'amad shloshtan. Because it basically can be seen as that I
put David in my place. I'm not just transferring the debt, I'm
making David my substitute. We're all here. I'm going to step away
and David's going to move into where I am and he's going
to be me now. Okay, if you conceptualize it—exactly, exactly. I'm out
of the picture.
Okay? So therefore, if now it works fully of מעמד שלשתן ma'amad
shloshtan and that's how I transfer the oral debt, why shouldn't that
work by קידושין? kiddushin? Okay, so I basically say, you know, say
David here is the woman I'm trying to marry, call him Davida.
Okay, and I say, Michael, that hundred dollars you owe me, you
give it to Davida and I'm going to marry Davida, you're married
to me with this hundred dollars. Okay, so with this, you know,
so therefore with this debt now, the money that Michael owes you,
not the money but the debt. Okay, so what should be the
problem? Michael can't be מוחל, mochel, I can't be מוחל, mochel, what
should be the problem? So the גמרא Gemara says like this. So
מר סבר, Mar savar, כי אמר רב, ki amar Rav, when does
רב Rav say that you can transfer something if they're all three
there? הני מילי בפקדון, hani mili bepikadon, that's when you're dealing with
an object that's taken for safekeeping, that it's a physical object. אבל
מלוה, aval milveh, but to transfer a debt, לא, lo, that can't
be transferred. ומר סבר, uMar savar, לא שנא מלוה ולא שנא פקדון,
lo shna milveh velo shna pikadon, it doesn't matter whether it's a
debt or whether it's an object for safekeeping, it can be transferred
and therefore a woman can be married. Again now what we've done
is we've taken
this debate of marrying a woman with a מלוה, milveh, according to
almost all the explanations of the גמרא, Gemara, has really nothing to
do with הלכות קידושין. hilchos kiddushin. It has to do with whether
you can—how you would transfer a debt and whether those criteria were
satisfied or not satisfied. Okay, now the גמרא's Gemara going to go
back to this issue about מקדש במלוה, mekadesh bemilveh, is this agreed
upon or is this debated? So the גמרא Gemara says, נימא כתנאי.
naima ketannai. Let's go back and say that this question of מקדש
במלוה mekadesh bemilveh is a debate of תנאים, Tannaim, since you rejected
the previous case by saying it was these other discussions and marrying
with a debt owed—that other people owe, let's try this debate of
תנאים. Tannaim. What's the reason of מעמד שלשתן? ma'amad shloshtan? Why would
there be a difference between פקדון pikadon and a מלוה? milveh? Again,
it's always easier to transfer a physical object and then you could
sort of
say—I know, but conceptually—okay. התקדשי לי בשטר. hiskadshi li beshtar. You say
to a woman, marry me with this document. רבי מאיר אומר אינה
מקודשת, Rabbi Meir omer eina mekudeshet, it doesn't work. רבי אליעזר אומר
מקודשת, Rabbi Eliezer omer mekudeshet, it does work. וחכמים אומרים, veChachamim omrim,
I was waiting for somebody to ask this before, שמינין את הנייר,
shamnin es hanyar, you evaluate the cost of the piece of paper.
אם יש בה שוה פרוטה מקודשת, im yesh bah shaveh perutah mekudeshet,
if the paper—you're not—you don't marry her with the debt in the
paper, but you're giving her a piece of paper. If that paper
is worth a פרוטה perutah מקודשת, mekudeshet, ואם לאו אינה מקודשת. veim
lav eina mekudeshet. Okay,
even though you didn't say you were marrying her with the value
of the paper, anyway, האי שטר היכי דמי? hai shtar heichi dami?
Now what is this שטר? shtar? אילימא שטר חוב דאחריני, ileima shtar
chov d'achreini, other people owe you money and so it's like the
case we said before, קשיא דרבי מאיר אדרבי מאיר, kashya d'Rabbi Meir
ad'Rabbi Meir, then it contradicts because before רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said
she's מקודשת mekudeshet when you marry her with a loan other people
owe you. Here רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says אינה מקודשת. eina mekudeshet.
Okay, so clearly we can't be—a loan other people owe you because
then the positions are reversed. אלא בשטר חוב דידה, ella beshtar chov
didah, it must be it's her I owe you, she owes you
money. במקדש במלוה קמיפלגי. bemekadesh bemilveh kamifligi. And the question is can
you be מקדש mekadesh her by giving her back her "I owe
you," which is just a nice physical representation of being מקדש במלוה,
mekadesh bemilveh, letting her keep the money she owes you. So that
seems to be—that's the debate now, we finally got it. You can't
make it other people because then רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would have
reversed himself. So we're left with saying this is being מקדש mekadesh
with the מלוה, milveh, with the money that she owes you. So
the גמרא Gemara gets out of it because notice it says, התקדשי
לי בשטר hiskadshi li beshtar
and it didn't say שטר חוב. shtar chov. So that opened the
door a crack and now let's see what the גמרא's Gemara going
to do. It's going to be an amazing read of this. אמר
רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, הכא במאי עסקינן,
hacha bemai askinan, כגון שקדשה בשטר שאין לו עדים. kigon shekidsha beshtar
she'ein lo eidim.
It's not a שטר חוב. shtar chov. What makes you think about
a שטר חוב? shtar chov? Because that's what we've been talking about.
But when you say, התקדשי לי בשטר, hiskadshi li beshtar, it means
what are the three ways a woman is married? כסף, שטר וביאה.
kesef, shtar, ve'biah. So basically, you take out a document and you
write הרי את מקודשת לי. harei at mekudeshet li. התקדשי לי בשטר.
hiskadshi li beshtar. Okay, who
else was talking about loans? Okay, so then what's the debate? The
debate is you didn't sign any witnesses to the document. But witnesses
were there at the time? Yes, but you didn't sign them, because
קידושין kiddushin needs witnesses. But you didn't sign them to the document.
Okay. רבי מאיר לטעמיה, Rabbi Meir letaimei,
so why does רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir say it's no good? He
goes according to his reasoning, דאמר עדי חתימה כרתי. d'amar edei chasimah
karsi. Remember by גט, get, you need the signatures to make it
a
legit— Without signed signatures, signed witnesses, it doesn't function as a שטר.
shtar. רבי אלעזר לטעמיה דאמר עדי מסירה כרתי. Rabbi Elazar letameih de'amar
edei mesirah kratei.
It's enough that the witnesses are present, so it was a good
שטר shtar and they were physically they were present and observing it.
Now ורבנן, verabbanan, the Rabbis who say that you gotta have the
piece of paper worth a פרוטה, prutah, נסתפקא להו, nistapka lehu, they're
uncertain. אי כרבי מאיר אי כרבי אלעזר. ee keRabbi Meir ee keRabbi
Elazar. Which way to go? הלכך, hilkach, therefore they say look, the
case which will definitely be good is שמיניה וניה, shemineiya veneiya, let's
forget how much the paper was worth. אם יש בו שווה פרוטה
מקודשת ואי לאו אינה מקודשת. im yesh bo shaveh prutah mekudeshet ve'ee
lav einah mekudeshet. If it were if it has a פרוטה prutah
it works, if not it doesn't work. Now, here's the problem רש"י
Rashi says. I don't understand. If it doesn't have a פרוטה, prutah,
it should be ספק מקודשת safek mekudeshet because it says the Rabbis
didn't know which way to go like רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar or
רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So רש"י Rashi cuts out the last word.
He says if it has a פרוטה prutah she's ודאי מקודשת. vadai
mekudeshet. If it doesn't have a פרוטה, prutah, it's not clear. But
the other question is why did the גמרא Gemara have to say
the Rabbis don't know? Let the גמרא Gemara say that the Rabbis
hold like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that if it's that fundamentally it's
not a שטר, shtar, because if it has a פרוטה prutah it
works as כסף, kesef, right? It's not clear why the גמרא Gemara
had to introduce the idea that the רבנן Rabbanan have a ספק.
safek. Probably because it's clear you're not trying to be מקדש mekadesh
her with the paper. You're trying to be מקדש mekadesh her with
the הרי את מקודשת לי. harei at mekudeshet lee. So therefore they
say, well, it makes sense that we should maybe see this as
קידושי כסף kidushei kesef as a backup if it's possible it works
anyway. Like if it definitely didn't work, we would not go by
the value of the paper. But if it's possible it worked anyway,
we could throw in well, it may also might work as כסף
kesef and therefore מקודשת. mekudeshet. So that's the רבנן, rabbanan, but basically
has nothing to do with מקדש במלווה, mekadesh bemilveh, it's fundamentally the
case of קידושי שטר. kidushei shtar. Yes. There are two questions. So
one is when they say the value of paper, do they mean
like you know I buy a packet of loose-leaf paper, how much
is each one worth, or is it this paper just has stuff
written on it, it's not worth anything anymore? Yeah, no, it would
only it would clearly be the current value in the way it's
written. And the other thing is like exactly that, like you know
he's not trying If I understand. So we'll get to that, right?
But you say fundamentally he wants to be מקדש mekadesh her, so
if any way that would work within the ways he's doing is
implicit or not? But I understand that's very questionable. So that's why
the גמרא Gemara presumably is combining it with a ספק safek that
it already worked. איבעית אימא Eibeis eima of the אותיות, oseiyos, right?
Yeah,
right. Well, or could have been brought into it. Anyway, איבעית אימא,
eibeis eima, to go according to שכתבו שלא לשמה. shekesavo shelo lishmah.
So now the same way before we used at least here it's
a debate about קידושין, Kiddushin, right? Before רב Rav said let's bring
in every debate about מכירת שטר חוב mechiras shtar chov and say
that's what they're debating. But here if you're talking about קידושי שטר,
kidushei shtar, at least we're talking about a הלכה halacha of קידושין.
Kiddushin. So let's talk about the possible debates that exist by קידושי
שטר. kidushei shtar. And that's what they're debating. So one possible debate
is do you need the עדים edim to be signed on the
שטר? shtar? Here's another possible thing that they could be debating. איבעית
אימא, Eibeis eima, if you want I'll tell you, כגון שכתבו שלא
לשמה. kegon shekesavo shelo lishmah. You wrote it, הרי את מקודשת לי,
harei at mekudeshet lee, but when I was writing this out, I
wasn't thinking about this particular woman, you know? I was starting to
go out on dates and I figured let me have a שטר
קידושין shtar Kiddushin in my back pocket for when I find the
right woman, okay? And I put it in my wallet, okay? And
then finally I was on a date, I said oh maybe this
one, and then I took it out and I said here let's
get married right now. What? You compare it to... So that's the
question. Do you need a שטר קידושין shtar Kiddushin to be written
לשמה? lishmah? Okay? שכתבו שלא לשמה. shekesavo shelo lishmah.
So the גמרא Gemara says,
where were we? דאמר ריש לקיש: De'amar Reish Lakish: שטר אירוסין שכתבו
שלא לשמה, shtar eirusin shekesavo shelo lishmah,
which is a way of saying שטר קידושין, shtar Kiddushin, the הרי
את מקודשת לי harei at mekudeshet lee written on a document, מהו?
mahu? הוויה ליציאה מקישנא. havayah liyetzi'ah makishna.
Do we connect it to a גט, get, becoming a wife and
going out of the house? מה יציאה בעינן
לשמה, mah yetzi'ah be'inan lishmah, the same way by גט get it
says וכתב לה vechasav lah and we say that means לשמה, lishmah,
it has to be written with that woman in mind, אף הוויה
נמי בעינן לשמה, af havayah nami be'inan lishmah, שטר קידושין shtar Kiddushin
also with that woman in mind.
או דילמא הוויה להדדי מקישנא, o dilma havayah lehadei makishna, or do
we say no, that we compare not גיטין Gittin to קידושין, Kiddushin,
but one form of קידושין Kiddushin to another form of קידושין. Kiddushin.
מה הוויה דכסף, mah havayah dekesef, the same way קידושין Kiddushin with
money לא בעינן לשמה, lo be'inan lishmah, the money wasn't minted with
her in mind, although now we're going to have twenty-dollar bills with
a woman in mind, okay but anyway, the money wasn't minted with
her in mind, אף הוויה דשטר לא בעינן לשמה. af havayah deshtar
lo be'inan lishmah. So therefore a שטר shtar it doesn't have to
be written with her in mind. Okay, so that was that was
the issue. I mean so ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says it is
לשמה, lishmah, but maybe that's what they're debating. It was written שלא
לשמה shelo lishmah and they're debating whether that works or not by
קידושין. Kiddushin. בתר דבעיא הדר פשטה. basar debeiya hadar pashta. That was
ריש לקיש's Reish Lakish's question. After ריש לקיש Reish Lakish raised the
question, he himself concluded
ויצאה והייתה, veyatze'ah vehaysah, מקיש הוויה ליציאה. makish havayah liyetzi'ah. No, no,
no, clearly it has to work like a גט get and there
has to be לשמה. lishmah. That's what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish concluded.
All right, I understand. That's what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish concluded. מר
אית ליה דריש לקיש, mar is leih deReish Lakish, one agrees with
him, that would be רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, and if it was
written שלא לשמה shelo lishmah it's no good. ומר לית ליה דריש
לקיש, umar leis leih deReish Lakish, and the חכמים Chachamim disagree or
whoever it was who disagreed there with רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי
אלעזר, Rabbi Elazar, and that's why it works so well to say
they were debating עדים. edim. The גט get and it has to
be לשמה. lishmah. That's what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish concluded. Right, I
understand. That's what ריש לקיש Reish Lakish concluded. So מר אית ליה
דרייש לקיש, Mar isleih deReish Lakish, one agrees with him, that would
be רבי מאיר. Rebbe Meir. And if it was written שלא לשמה,
shelo lishmah, it's no good. ומר לית ליה דרייש לקיש, Umar leitleih
deReish Lakish, and the חכמים Chachamim disagree, or whoever it was who
disagreed with רבי מאיר, Rebbe Meir, רבי אליעזר. Rebbe Eliezer. Actually, that's
why it worked so well to say they were debating עדי מסירה
Eidei Mesirah or עדי חתימה, Eidei Chasimah, because it was the exact
same רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir and רבי אליעזר. Rebbe Eliezer. So one
way of framing the debate is it's the classic רבי מאיר, Rebbe
Meir, רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer debate, עדי מסירה Eidei Mesirah or עדי
חתימה, Eidei Chasimah, which is exactly the two that are debating about
this מקדש בשטר. mekadesh beshtar. The other way is it's another debate.
רבי מאיר Rebbe Meir requires לשמה, lishmah, and רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer
does not require
לשמה. lishmah. Okay. ואיבעית אימא דכולי עלמא אית להו דרייש לקיש, V'iba'is
eima dechulei alma is lehu deReish Lakish, you know what, I could
say everybody agrees with ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, you need
לשמה. lishmah. והכא במאי עסקינן? V'hacha b'mai askinan? So there are עדים
eideim written in the document, it's the document is written לשמה. lishmah.
What's left to be debated? The following thing: שכתבו לשמה ושלא מדעתה.
Sheketavo lishmah veshelo mida'atah. You wrote it with her in mind but
without her awareness. So here I am, I'm dating this woman and
I'm hoping she's going to marry me but I haven't proposed yet.
So I'm going to write הרי את מקודשת Harei at mekudeshes with
her specifically in mind, but she has no idea. Like it's going
to be three months down before I pop the question, okay? So
does that work? Okay? לשמה ושלא מדעתה. Lishmah veshelo mida'atah. Well, would
that work by גט? get? What?
Alright, well let's take a look. Okay. ובפלוגתא דרבה ורבינא ורב פפא
ורב
שרביא קמיפלגי. Uviflugeta deRabbah veRavina veRav Papa veRav Sharvya kamiflegi. And it's
debated, this debate of אמוראים. Amoraim. דאיתמר, De'itmar, it was said: כתבו
לשמה ושלא מדעתה. Ketavo lishmah veshelo mida'atah. It was written with her
in mind but without her awareness. רבה ורבינא אמרי מקודשת, Rabbah veRavina
amri mekudeshes, it works. רב פפא ורב שרביא אמרי אינה מקודשת, Rav
Papa veRav Sharvya amri einah mekudeshes, it doesn't work. So נימא כהני
תנאי. Neima kahanei tanna'ei. Now let's say that this debate is like
the following debate. Okay.
I'm sorry. So I'm sorry, no, no, period, that's the end. So
what is the debate about? So the גמרא Gemara here doesn't say,
but elsewhere the גמרא Gemara says the debate is the following. The
most obvious thing to say is what Michael said. It's like a
גט; get; a גט get doesn't have to be written with her
knowledge, this doesn't have to be written with her knowledge. But there's
two differences. The first most obvious difference is a גט get is
a one-sided transaction. It's against her will, she's completely passive. So I'm
the person totally in control, she doesn't have to be aware and
part of the process. קידושין, Kiddushin, she has to say yes and
she has to be part of the process. Maybe the writing has
to be with her effectively, you know, brought into the process. The
thing that the גמרא Gemara says to make it even stronger, it
is that idea but even
stronger, is who's the seller? Okay?
This actually makes a שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin very strange. When I
sell you my plot of land, right, who writes the שטר, shtar,
the seller or the buyer? The seller. שדי מכורה לך. Sadi mechurah
lach. Okay? So when the woman gets married to the man, if
the man is giving money and you're looking at it in the
קנין kinyan model, who's the seller? The woman. She's selling herself to
the man. So she should be the one, she should write the
one אני מקודשת לך, Ani mekudeshes lach, right? She should be the
one. But no, but because he's the active party, he writes הרי
את מקודשת לי. Harei at mekudeshes li. But she's still the seller,
even though he's writing the שטר. shtar. So because she's the seller
and a classic definition of a שטר shtar is שטר מקנה, shtar
makneh, a שטר shtar written by the authority of the one who
is obligating himself or selling or so on, so therefore she has
to be part of the process. Not just because she's going to
have to say yes, but because in some ways she might even
really be the בעל השטר. ba'al hashtar. Okay, which is a very
interesting thing when you put those two models together: the גט get
and this sense of him controlling everything, and on the other hand
the sense that she's the seller. Okay, so that's the debate. Okay.
So this leads to the, so then but the money also then
you'd say I'm going to give you the money, you have to
tell her that beforehand too? No, no, no. Any transaction is you
give me money and I take the money and I'm selling you
my field. You give me money and I'm marrying myself. But you
didn't see that she has to know in advance that he's going
to write a שטר. shtar. No, no, no, no. But הלכה halacha
is that the שטר shtar is only a good שטר shtar if
written under the authority of the seller. That's the הלכה. halacha. Okay.
What? A slave too wouldn't write his own שטר, shtar, would he?
Correct. But a slave isn't, well you know, שטר shtar sale, yeah
but I can't process that right now. It's a good question. Okay,
anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, anyway, so that
ברייתא braita was not debating מקדש במלווה. mekadesh bemilveh. We have one
case where they were debating מקדש mekadesh with money owed, somebody else
owes me. We have another case of debating marrying a woman with
a שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin and what's required of a שטר קידושין.
shtar kiddushin. But we have yet to pin down this idea of
רב Rav of מקדש במלווה mekadesh bemilveh into a debate of תנאים.
Tanna'im. But we're not giving up. נימא כהני תנאי. Neima kahanei tanna'ei.
Maybe it's like these תנאים. Tanna'im. דתניא, Detanya, as we learned in
a ברייתא: braita: עשי לי שירים נזמים וטבעות. Asi li shirim nezamim
v'taba'os. You say to
a, woman says to a man, you know what? This guy's a
jeweler. Make for me some earrings and rings and whatever, ואקדש אני
לך. ve'ekadesh ani lach. And here's some gold, here's some silver, fashion
these into some rings and jewelry, and with this service that you're
doing for me, I'll be married to you. Okay. I got the
scenario? Okay, great. And then he gives her the rings back, but
it was her gold. Has he given her anything? Yes. He's given
her the service. Okay, so it's worth more now. Ah, so that's
interesting, but that's an interesting question of who owns the, maybe, maybe
the original owner owns the increase, automatically gets the increase in value.
When you go ahead and you work on my house and my
house goes up a hundred thousand dollars, you don't own that increase
in value, you're just owed the value of, you know, the contract,
the value of your labor. Okay, so basically what this guy's... Giving
is he's giving the labor. But do we look at it that
he's giving her the labor, or do we look at it as
I owe you a hundred dollars for the labor and I'm מקדש
mekadesh you, excuse me, you owe, how does it work? I owe
you a hundred, I the woman, right, owe you a hundred dollars
for the labor and therefore by you giving me the hundred dollars
back, you're being מקדש mekadesh me. So that's מקדש במלווה. mekadesh bemilveh.
Right.
Well, we didn't. All we said is do this for me and
then I'll agree to be married to you. Okay, that's what the
woman said. He didn't even say that, "I'm מקדש mekadesh you with
the value," right? He doesn't say anything here. No. So that's the
question, what's going on? Okay, let's take a look. She says, "Do
this service for me and then I'll be married to you." Okay.
So כיוון שעשה מקודשת, keivan she'asah mekudeshet, once you make the rings
and presumably hand them over, she's מקודשת, mekudeshet, דברי רבי מאיר. divrei
rabbi meir. That's what Rabbi Meir says. וחכמים אומרים אינה מקודשת עד
שיגיע ממון לידה. vachachamim omrim eina mekudeshet ad sheyagia mamon leyadah. She's
not מקודשת mekudeshet until the money goes into her hands. So האי
ממון היכי דמי, hai mamon heichi dami, what money are we talking
about that's going into her hands? אילימא אותו ממון, eilima oto mamon,
the rings, like the money that, you know, the precious things that
are being given over and now the objects themselves. מכלל דתנא קמא
סבר אפילו אותו ממון נמי לא. michlal detanna kamma savar afilu oto
mamon nami lo. So does that mean when the תנא קמא tanna
kamma says she is מקודשת, mekudeshet, it's before he gave her back
the rings? אלא במה
מקדשה? ella bemah mekadesha? So what's he marrying her with? Meaning he
hasn't even completed his service until he finishes the job and gives
it over. So there's nothing yet to marry her, there's no money
owed for the service, like nothing. The rings, like... The assumption is
not. I understand. Let's just read. Okay, the assumption is that there
would not yet be any services rendered until the thing is done
and handed back over. Okay, אלא לאו בממון אחרינא, ella lav bemamon
achrina, but what it must mean is that the חכמים chachamim are
saying is this service doesn't count and if you want to marry
her, give her some other money, but anything you did here doesn't
work. Okay, so what's the issue? ובמקדש במלווה קמיפלגי, ubimekadesh bemilveh kamipalgi,
presumably really all that's here is that he performed a service, so
she owes him money, and then he's saying keep the money. So
that's מקדש במלווה. mekadesh bemilveh. So the גמרא gemara says דסברי, desabri,
but reading it that way presumes, and now the גמרא gemara is
already telling you how this is not the only way to read
it, to read it that it's מקדש במלווה mekadesh bemilveh presumes דסברי
כולי עלמא ישנה לשכירות מתחילה ועד סוף והווה מלווה, desabri kulei alma
yeshnah liskirus mitechilah ve'ad sof vahavah milveh,
that the debt is incurred from beginning to end and therefore it
is a loan, which means what? Okay, Michael comes to work on
my house or on my rings or on my car, okay, and
rather than paying him for the job, which we'll see in a
minute would be a different story, I'm going to pay him hourly.
Okay, and I agree to pay him ten dollars an hour but
it's payable, okay, when the job is done. Okay, and then the
job is done after ten hours of service. So what's the story?
Until that last minute, I owe him zero? And at that last
minute I owe him a hundred dollars? Or is it every, you
know, hour I owe him another ten dollars but I don't have
to start paying until he's done with the job? So that's the
question of ישנה לשכירות מתחילה ועד סוף, yeshnah liskirus mitechilah ve'ad sof,
does the debt start being incurred for the services rendered start from
the very beginning or only the debt only comes at the end?
So how's it different? If the debt is incurred every minute along
the way, okay, so then when the job is done, now all
that's left is I owe you a hundred, you know, is debts
that were incurred in the past, right? So the guy can't be
giving her his service, right? The service, you know, all that happened
was that by doing the service it incurred a debt and now
she owes him money. All he can do is say keep the
money you owe me. But if nothing is, there's no debt, there's
no obligation until the end, so now that the guy is finished,
he says, "I am giving you my service," meaning rather than having
this become a debt, forget the debt, just just my service is
a gift to you, right? So that's not מקדש במלווה. mekadesh bemilveh.
Understand, is that clear? Okay, because the service is now completed at
the end of it. Right. But, so rather than saying this is...
right, so what he's giving her now is not that now she
owes a hundred dollars and he says forget it, right? Because nothing
was owed until this last minute. And at this last minute he
says, "Just keep the service, the service is my gift to you."
Okay, so that's whereas if... what... we don't see him saying anything.
I understand, so the question is now what he says, it's how
do we interpret what's happening here. All she does is she says
"Do this and I'll be מקודשת mekudeshet to you." He says "Fine"
and he does it. So do it... so what's happening? If the
debt was being incurred along the way, then the only thing that's
happening he could be doing is giving... is being מוחל mochel the
debt or giving her back the money. Okay, but otherwise he's giving
her the service. That's the question. Okay, so גמרא gemara says לא,
lo, now you've opened up the door to have different interpretations. Rather
than saying that everybody says it's a debt and the question is
מקדש במלווה, mekadesh bemilveh, there's other ways of saying it. דכולי עלמא
מקדש במלווה אינה מקודשת, dekulei alma mekadesh bemilveh eina mekudeshet, everybody could
agree it doesn't work if it's a מלווה. milveh. ואכא בישנה לשכירות
מתחילה ועד סוף קמיפלגי. ve'acha biyeshnah liskirus mitechilah ve'ad sof kamipalgi. The
question is whether the debt starts being incurred from the beginning of
the service or only at the end. מר סבר אינה לשכירות אלא
בסוף, mar savar einah liskirus ella besof, the obligation only comes at
the end so it's not really a debt.
you don't owe me any money. Okay, no, I did it and
you don't owe me money. My service was my gift, and therefore
it works. Okay, אלא בסוף. ela besof. ומר סבר U'mar savar ישנה
לשכירות מתחלה ועד סוף. yeshna l'sichirus mitchila v'ad sof. No, the debt
was accruing all along and therefore what he's giving her now is
he's giving her back the debt and therefore it doesn't work. ואיבעית
תימא V'ibayis teima I'm going to have no questions until we get
to the משנה. Mishnah. Okay, we have five minutes. ואיבעית תימא V'ibayis
teima דכולי עלמא d'chulei alma ישנה לשכירות מתחלה ועד סוף. yeshna l'sichirus
mitchila v'ad sof. Everybody says it's from beginning to end, which means
that there is a debt. ומקדש במלוה אינה מקודשת U'mekadesh b'milve einah
mekudeshet and you can't marry with a מלוה. milve. So what's what
are you left with? והכא V'hacha the question that Michael was asking,
באומן קונה בשבח כלי קמיפלגי. b'uman koneh b'shvach kli kamifligi.
I'm not paying by the hour, I'm paying for the job. Okay,
so I say Michael take my car and fix the carburetor and
we've agreed on a non-hourly thing, two hundred dollars for the job.
Okay, so Michael does the job. Before I've paid him the two
hundred dollars, there's two ways of looking at it. I just owe
him my car has now worth more and I owe him two
hundred dollars. That's probably the natural way of looking at it. But
the other way of looking at it is because he made the
improvement in the car and he wasn't being paid hourly, right, where
it would be sort of seen essentially as him being my like
sort of my labor as it were, it's more he takes possession
of it and makes the improvement. He's being paid for the job.
He actually now owns the increased value of the car. He just
has to now sell it to me for the two hundred dollars
we agreed on. But if he doesn't I don't pay him the
two hundred dollars, he now has a two hundred dollar stake or
maybe it's worth more. The car maybe has now improved four hundred
dollars. He has that stake in my car. אומן קונה בשבח כלי,
Uman koneh b'shvach kli, I mean, you see the car's maybe not
as good an example. You certainly see it like in home improvements
or like the ring, right, where the amount of labor that went
in, the amount I'm paying is less than the increased value of
the object. Okay. So, אומן קונה בשבח כלי קמיפלגי. Uman koneh b'shvach
kli kamifligi. מר סבר אומן קונה בשבח כלי, Mar savar uman koneh
b'shvach kli, so actually the jeweler now owns a piece of the
ring. And now he's just agreed to sell it back to her
essentially for the two hundred dollars they agreed on. So he says
you know what, don't give me the two hundred dollars, take the
ring, take the new value.
So the ownership I have, I have a partial ownership now in
that ring. I'm giving over the ring to you. Okay. And now
she becomes a full owner of the ring. Okay. So that he's
really מקדש mekadesh her with something concrete. מר סבר אומן קונה בשבח
כלי Mar savar uman koneh b'shvach kli ומר סבר אינו אומן קונה
בשבח כלי. U'mar savar eino uman koneh b'shvach kli. No, he doesn't
own any piece of the ring, and all he has is the
money owed to him, and that would be מקדש במלוה. mekadesh b'milve.
Okay. So that's another way of interpreting it. ואיבעית תימא V'ibayis teima
if you want you can say דכולי עלמא אינו אומן קונה בשבח
כלי. d'chulei alma eino uman koneh b'shvach kli. He doesn't own a
piece of the ring. וישנה לשכירות מתחלה ועד סוף V'yeshna l'sichirus mitchila
v'ad sof and the debt is being accrued from the beginning. So
it's a
debt. Okay. ומקדש במלוה אינה מקודשת U'mekadesh b'milve einah mekudeshet and you
can't be מקדש mekadesh with a מלוה milve because the גמרא Gemara
noticed is trying to make it that everybody agrees with רב Rav
that מקדש במלוה אינה מקודשת. mekadesh b'milve einah mekudeshet. So everybody agrees
it's a debt, you can't be מקדש במלוה, mekadesh b'milve, it's not
a case of paying for the job and it's not a case
and even if it were the אומן uman doesn't own any piece
of the ring. So what is possible to be מקדש mekadesh her
with? והכא במאי עסקינן V'hacha b'mai askinan what are you talking about?
כגון שהוסיף בה נופך משלו. Kigon shehosif bah nofach mishelo. What he
did is he said you gave me a piece of gold but
I loved you so much, I went and I put in a
little precious stone of my own. Okay. I made my own little
addition to this ring, not what we contracted about. Okay. So I
can't be מקדש mekadesh to you with the money you owe me.
I can't be מקדש mekadesh you with the value of the ring
because of the improvements I made that you were paid for. But
can I be מקדש mekadesh you with this extra little you know
amethyst or whatever that I added to the ring which you didn't
ask for? דמר סבר מלוה ופרוטה דעתיה אפרוטה, D'mar savar milve u'perutah
daiteih a'perutah, that basically when he's giving it everything to her, he's
giving her back the two hundred dollars that she owes him and
this extra little ten dollar addition. So do we say in that
case it's sort of like the case of the value of the
שטר shtar that fundamentally the way it's thought about is he's trying
to be מקדש mekadesh her with the bigger amount, with the two
hundred dollars, and that little ten dollar addition he made is trivial
and that can't work as
כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. Okay. מר סבר מלוה ופרוטה דעתיה אפרוטה. Mar
savar milve u'perutah daiteih a'perutah. No, she could still be focusing on
or halachically we'll say that it's significant, this concrete little פרוטה perutah
that he added to it and that is and that does work
as
כסף קידושין. kesef kiddushin. ומר סבר דעתיה אמלוה U'mar savar daiteih a'milve
fundamentally it's about the bigger amount, the other stuff is trivial and
therefore she's not מקודשת mekudeshet even though he gave her this little
five dollar amethyst. Okay. ובפלוגתא דהני תנאי U'v'plugta d'hanei tanna'ei and that
debate about מלוה ופרוטה milve u'perutah which we've referred to before fits
into this following debate. דתניא D'tanya we taught in a ברייתא. Baraisa.
בשכר שעשיתי עמך אינה מקודשת. B'schar she'asisi imach einah mekudeshet. If somebody
says marry me with the money you owe me for the labor
I performed, okay that's like מקדש במלוה, mekadesh b'milve, it doesn't work.
בשכר שאעשה עמך מקודשת B'schar she'e'eseh imach mekudeshet with the for
pay me with the money you'll owe me for the service I
will perform מקודשת mekudeshet that does work. That's sort of like what
we just talked about. רבי נתן אומר בשכר שאעשה עמך אינה מקודשת,
Rebbi Nasan omer b'schar she'e'eseh imach einah mekudeshet, even that doesn't work.
work. וכל שכן ve-chol sheken בשכר שעשיתי עמך, bischar she-asisi imcha, certainly
the labor I've already performed, which is a
מלווה. milveh. רבי יהודה נשיא אומר, Rebbi Yehuda Nasi omer, באמת אמרו,
be-emes amru, in fact they've said, בין בשכר שעשיתי, bein bischar she-asisi,
בין בשכר שאעשה, bein bischar she-ese,
whether the money you owe me or whether the money you will
owe me for service to be performed עמך, imcha, אינה מקודשת, einah
mekudeshet, like רבי נתן Rebbi Natan says, both of those don't work.
However, ואם הוסיף לה נופך משלו, ve-im hosif lah nofach mishelo, if
he adds a little thing of his own, then מקודשת, mekudeshet, it
does work. So this is exactly how we framed it, and now
the גמרא Gemara is going to explain. בין לתנא קמא לבין רבי
נתן איכא בינייהו שכירות. bein le-Tanna Kamma le-vein Rebbi Natan ika beinihu
schirus. What's the debate about? Everybody says you can't marry her based
on the money already owed, that's מקדש במלווה. mekadesh be-milveh. What's the
debate of can you marry her with the service to be performed?
That's the question of שכירות מתחילה ועד סוף, schirus mi-techilla ve-ad sof,
and that even when it gets, even though you're talking about it
before performing it, by the time it's done, it just becomes a
debt, and it's מקדש במלווה. mekadesh be-milveh. Or do we say אין
לשכירות אלא לבסוף? ein li-schirus ella le-vasof? It means when you're done,
you're giving her the שכירות. schirus. You're giving her the service. It
never became a debt; you're giving her the service. That's that debate.
Okay, בין רבי נתן לרבי יהודה נשיא, bein Rebbi Natan le-Rebbi Yehuda
Nasi, and
how about the issue about when you add a little thing to
it which wasn't paid for? איכא בינייהו מלווה ופרוטה. ika beinihu milveh
u-perutah. When there's a big loan and you're giving a פרוטה. perutah.
מר סבר מלווה ופרוטה דעתיה אהמלווה, mar savar milveh u-perutah da-atei a-ha-milveh,
that no, that's fundamentally it's about the loan that you're trying and
that doesn't work, so she's אינה מקודשת. einah mekudeshet. ומר סבר דעתיה
אהפרוטה, u-mar savar da-atei a-ha-perutah, no, because there's also a פרוטה perutah
that also works, and because there's a little thing that is actually
new that's being given, that's ככסף קידושין. ke-chesef kiddushin. To some degree
it's a little bit like the שטר, shtar, does the piece of
paper work? But here it's different, because the piece of paper, the
value of the paper for the שטר shtar is less likely to
work, because fundamentally you're thinking about it as, I don't know, as
a שטר קידושין. shtar kiddushin. You know, and this is a completely
unrelated issue. Here it's a big package, and although this is a
tiny piece of the big package, it's still all value that is
being given to her. Okay, so that's the debate, and the גמרא
Gemara concludes מקדש במלווה אינה מקודשת. mekadesh be-milveh einah mekudeshet. Even though
it seems like a debate of תנאים, Tannaim, we got everybody to
agree that it was אינה מקודשת, einah mekudeshet, and that is the
way that we rule.